Do you think the world is going to be a better place next year?
هل تعتقدون أن العالم سوف يكون مكان أفضل في السنة القادمة؟
In the next decade?
في العقد القادم؟
Can we end hunger,
هل يمكنا القضاء على الجوع،
achieve gender equality,
تحقيق المساواة بين الجنسين،
halt climate change,
وقف تغير المناخ،
all in the next 15 years?
كل هذا خلال 15 سنة القادمة؟
Well, according to the governments of the world, yes we can.
وِفقا لحكومات دول العالم، نعم نستطيع.
In the last few days, the leaders of the world,
في الأيام القليلة الأخيرة، قادة العالم،
meeting at the UN in New York,
التقوا في الأمم المتحدة في نيويورك،
agreed a new set of Global Goals
واتفقوا على وضع مجموعة أهداف عالمية جديدة
for the development of the world to 2030.
لتنمية العالم حتى عام ٢٠٣٠.
And here they are:
تلك الأهداف كالتالي:
these goals are the product of a massive consultation exercise.
هذه الأهداف هي نتاج عملية تشاور واسعة النطاق.
The Global Goals are who we, humanity, want to be.
تلك الأهداف العالمية هي ماذا تريد الإنسانية أن تكون؟
Now that's the plan, but can we get there?
والآن هذه هي الخطة، لكن هل بإمكاننا آن نكون هناك؟
Can this vision for a better world really be achieved?
هل من الممكن فعلاً أن تتحقق تلك الرؤية ؟
Well, I'm here today because we've run the numbers,
حسناً، أنا هنا اليوم لأننا أجرينا حسابات لذلك،
and the answer, shockingly,
والجواب بشكلٍ صادم،
is that maybe we actually can.
هو أننا ربما بالفعل نستطيع.
But not with business as usual.
ولكن ليس بالمعاملات التجارية كالعادة.
Now, the idea that the world is going to get a better place
والآن، فكرة أن العالم سيصبح مكانا أفضل
may seem a little fanciful.
ربما تبدو وهميّة.
Watch the news every day and the world seems to be going backwards, not forwards.
شاهد الأخبار كل يوم وستلاحظ أن العالم يسير إلى الوراء وليس إلى الأمام.
And let's be frank:
ولنكن صريحين:
it's pretty easy to be skeptical about grand announcements
إنه من السهل أن تكون لديك بعض الشكوك حول التصريحات الكبرى
coming out of the UN.
الآتية من الولايات المتحدة.
But please, I invite you to suspend your disbelief for just a moment.
ولكن أرجوكم، أوقفوا شكوككم للحظة.
Because back in 2001,
لأنه بالعودة لعام 2001،
the UN agreed another set of goals, the Millennium Development Goals.
وافقت الولايات المتحدة على مجموعة أخرى من الأهداف، وهي الأهداف الإنمائية للألفية.
And the flagship target there was to halve the proportion of people
والهدف الرئيسي كان تخفيض نسبة السكان
living in poverty by 2015.
الذين يعيشون الفقر بحلول 2015.
The target was to take from a baseline of 1990,
والهدف كان الأخذ من منطلق 1990،
when 36 percent of the world's population lived in poverty,
عندما عاش 36% من السكان في الفقر،
to get to 18 percent poverty this year.
لتصل إلى 18% هذه السنة.
Did we hit this target?
هل حققنا هذا الهدف؟
Well, no, we didn't.
في الحقيقة، لا، لم نحقق ذلك.
We exceeded it.
لقد تجاوزنا ذلك.
This year, global poverty is going to fall to 12 percent.
هذه السنة، سينخفض الفقر العالمي إلى 12%.
Now, that's still not good enough,
حاليا، ما يزال هذا ليس جيدا بما يكفي،
and the world does still have plenty of problems.
وما يزال العالم مليئا بالمشاكل.
But the pessimists and doomsayers who say that the world can't get better
ولكن المتشائمين الذين يقولون بأن العالم لا يمكن أن يكون أفضل
are simply wrong.
هم بكلّ بساطة مُخطئون.
So how did we achieve this success?
إذن كيف تمكنا من تحقيق هذا النجاح؟
Well, a lot of it was because of economic growth.
في الحقيقة، الكثير من ذلك كان بسبب النمو الاقتصادي.
Some of the biggest reductions in poverty were in countries such as China and India,
بعض أكبر الانخفاضات في الفقر كانت في بلدان مثل الصين والهند،
which have seen rapid economic growth in recent years.
والتي شهدت نموا اقتصاديا سريعا في السنوات الأخيرة.
So can we pull off the same trick again?
هل يمكننا أن نجعل نفس الحيلة تنجح مرة أخرى؟
Can economic growth get us to the Global Goals?
هل يمكن أن يوصلنا النمو الإقتصادي إلى الأهداف العالمية؟
Well, to answer that question,
حسنا، للإجابة على ذلك السؤال،
we need to benchmark where the world is today against the Global Goals
نحن في حاجة لمراجعة مكانة العالم اليوم في تحقيق الأهداف العالمية
and figure out how far we have to travel.
ومعرفة المسافة المتبقية التي علينا غبورها.
But that ain't easy,
ولكن هذا ليس سهلا،
because the Global Goals aren't just ambitious,
لأن الأهداف العالمية ليست مجرد طموح،
they're also pretty complicated.
ولكنها أيضا معقدة جدا.
Over 17 goals, there are then 169 targets
أكثر من 17 غاية فتصبح الأهداف 169 هدفا
and literally hundreds of indicators.
بالإضافة للمئات من المؤشرات.
Also, while some of the goals are pretty specific --
وأيضا بينما تكون بعض الأهداف محدّدة جدّا --
end hunger --
القضاء على الجوع مثلا--
others are a lot vaguer --
إلا إن بعضها غامضة جدا --
promote peaceful and tolerant societies.
مثل تعزيز المجتمعات السلمية والمتسامحة.
So to help us with this benchmarking,
لذلك لمساعدتنا على هذه المقارنة،
I'm going to use a tool called the Social Progress Index.
سأستعمل وسيلة تُسمّى مُؤشّر النمو الاجتماعي.
What this does is measures all the stuff the Global Goals are trying to achieve,
يقيس هذا المؤشر كل الأشياء التي تسعى الأهداف العالمية لتحقيقها،
but sums it up into a single number that we can use as our benchmark
ولكن يُلخّصها في عدد واحد يمكن استعماله خلال المقارنة
and track progress over time.
وتتبّع التطور مع الوقت.
The Social Progress Index basically asks three fundamental questions
يطرح ٍ مُؤشّر النمو الاجتماعي 3 أسئلة
about a society.
أساسية حول المجتمع.
First of all, does everyone have the basic needs of survival:
أولا، هل يتمتع الجميع بأساسيات العيش:
food, water, shelter, safety?
الطعام والماء والمأوى والأمان؟
Secondly, does everyone have the building blocks of a better life:
ثانيا، هل يتمتع الجميع بعناصر البناء لحياة أفضل:
education, information, health and a sustainable environment?
التعليم والإعلام والصحة وبيئة مستدامة؟
And does everyone have the opportunity to improve their lives,
وهل يملك الجميع الفرصة لتحسين حياتهم،
through rights, freedom of choice, freedom from discrimination,
باعتماد الحقوق وحريّة الإختيار والتحرر من التمييز،
and access to the world's most advanced knowledge?
والحصول على المعرفة العالمية المتطورة؟
The Social Progress Index sums all this together using 52 indicators
يُلخّص مُؤشّر النموالاجتماعي كلّ هذا في 52 مُؤشرا
to create an aggregate score on a scale of 0 to 100.
لإنشاء نتيجة إجمالية تتراوح بين 0 و100.
And what we find is that there's a wide diversity of performance
ووجدنا تنوّعا في الأداء
in the world today.
في العالم اليوم.
The highest performing country, Norway, scores 88.
البلد الذي يشهد أكبر أداء هو النرويج بمعدل 88.
The lowest performing country, Central African Republic, scores 31.
والبلد ذو الأداء الأدنى هو جمهورية إفريقيا الوسطى، بمعدل 31.
And we can add up all the countries together,
ويمكننا جمع كل الدول معا،
weighting for the different population sizes,
لترجيح مختلف أحجام السكان،
and that global score is 61.
والمعدل العالمي هو 61.
In concrete terms,
وبشكل ملموس،
that means that the average human being is living on a level of social progress
هذا يعني أن متوسط الأشخاص يعيشون في مستوى النمو الإجتماعي
about the same of Cuba or Kazakhstan today.
تماما كما في كوبا وكازخستان اليوم.
That's where we are today: 61 out of 100.
هذا ما نحن عليه اليوم: 61 من 100.
What do we have to get to to achieve the Global Goals?
ما الذي يجب علينا القيام به لتحقيق الأهداف العالية؟
Now, the Global Goals are certainly ambitious,
حاليا، الأهداف العالمية هي بالتأكيد تدلّ على الطموح،
but they're not about turning the world into Norway in just 15 years.
ولكن ليست تحويل العالم إلى النرويج في 15 عاما فقط.
So having looked at the numbers, my estimate is that a score of 75
إذن بالنظر إلى الأرقام، حسب تقديري معدل 75
would not only be a giant leap forward in human well-being,
لن يكون قفزة نوعية في صالح رفاهة الإنسان فقط،
it would also count as hitting the Global Goals target.
وإنما كتحقيق للأهداف العالمية.
So there's our target, 75 out of 100.
إذن هدفنا هو 75 من 100.
Can we get there?
هل يمكننا الوصول إلى هناك؟
Well, the Social Progress Index can help us calculate this,
حسنا، يمكن أن يساعدنا مؤشرالنمو الاجتماعي
because as you might have noticed,
على حساب هذا لأنه وكما لاحظتم،
there are no economic indicators in there;
لا توجد مؤشرات اقتصادية،
there's no GDP or economic growth in the Social Progress Index model.
ليس هناك ناتج محلي إجمالي أو نمو اقتصادي بمؤشر النمو الاجتماعي.
And what that lets us do is understand the relationship
وهذا ما يُحيلنا إلى فهم العلاقة
between economic growth and social progress.
بين النمو الاقتصادي والنمو الاجتماعي.
Let me show you on this chart.
دعوني أريكم ذلك على هذا المخطط.
So here on the vertical axis, I've put social progress,
إذن وضعت على المحور العمودي النمو الاجتماعي،
the stuff the Global Goals are trying to achieve.
الأشياء التي تسعى الأهداف العالمية إلى تحقيقها.
Higher is better.
كلما كان ذلك أعلى كان أحسن.
And then on the horizontal axis, is GDP per capita.
وعلى المحور الأفقي، متوسط الفرد من الناتج المحلي الإجمالي.
Further to the right means richer.
أقرب إلى اليمين بمعنى أغنى.
And in there, I'm now going to put all the countries of the world,
وهناك سوف أضع كل بلدان العالم،
each one represented by a dot,
كل بلد سأمثّله بنقطة،
and on top of that I'm going to put the regression line
وفي الأعلى سأضع خط الانحدار
that shows the average relationship.
الذي يبيّن العلاقة التقريبية.
And what this tells us is that as we get richer,
وهذا يخبرنا بأننا كلما نصبح أغنى،
social progress does tend to improve.
يتحسن النمو الاجتماعي.
However, as we get richer, each extra dollar of GDP
بينما، كلما أصبحنا أغنى، كل دولار إضافي من الناتج المحلي الإجمالي
is buying us less and less social progress.
يشتري لنا أقل وأقل نمو اجتماعي.
And now we can use this information to start building our forecast.
والآن نستطيع استعمال هذه المعلومة لنبدأ في بناء توقّعاتنا.
So here is the world in 2015.
إذن هذا ما سيكون عليه العالم في سنة 2015.
We have a social progress score of 61
ارتفع معدّل النموالاجتماعي ليبلغ 61
and a GDP per capita of $14,000.
ومعدّل الناتج المحلي الاجمالي للفرد الواحد 14,000$.
And the place we're trying to get to, remember, is 75, that Global Goals target.
والمعدّل الذي نسعى إلى بلوغه، تذكّروا، هو 75، ذلك هو هدف الأهداف العالمية.
So here we are today, $14,000 per capita GDP.
بلغ إلى حدّ اليوم، معدّل الناتج المحلي الإجمالي للفرد 14,000$.
How rich are we going to be in 2030?
كم سنصبح أغنى في عام 2030؟
That's what we need to know next.
هذا ما نحتاج معرفته مستقبلا.
Well, the best forecast we can find comes from the US Department of Agriculture,
حسنا، أفضل التوقّعات تأتينا من وزارة الزراعة الأمريكية،
which forecasts 3.1 percent average global economic growth
والتي تكهّنت بمتوسّط نموّ اقتصادي يبلغ 3.1 %
over the next 15 years,
خلال 15 سنة المقبلة،
which means that in 2030, if they're right,
وهذا يعني أنه في سنة 2030، إذا كان ذلك صحيحا،
per capita GDP will be about $23,000.
سيكون معدّل الناتج المحلي الإجمالي للفرد 23,000$.
So now the question is: if we get that much richer,
إذن السؤال الآن هو: إذا بلغنا هذا الحجم من الثراء،
how much social progress are we going to get?
ماهو مدى النمو الاجتماعي الذي سنبلغه؟
Well, we asked a team of economists at Deloitte
حسنا، سألنا مجموعة من المختصين الاقتصاديين
who checked and crunched the numbers,
بديلويت الذين عاينوا الأرقام وعالجوها
and they came back and said, well, look: if the world's average wealth goes
حيث رجعوا وقالوا، حسنا، انظروا إذا كان معدّل ثروة العالم
from $14,000 a year to $23,000 a year,
يرتفع من 14,000 $ في السنة إلى 23,000$ في السنة،
social progress is going to increase
فإن النمو الإجتماعي سيشهد ارتفاعا
from 61 to 62.4.
من 61 إلى 62.4.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Just 62.4. Just a tiny increase.
فقط 62.4، إنه ارتفاع ضئيل.
Now this seems a bit strange.
حاليا يبدو هذا غريبا قليلا.
Economic growth seems to have really helped
يبدو أن النمو الاقتصادي ساعد حقا
in the fight against poverty,
في المعركة ضد الفقر،
but it doesn't seem to be having much impact
ولكن لا يبدو أن لهذا تأثير هامّ فيما يتعلق
on trying to get to the Global Goals.
بمحاولة تحقيق الأهداف العالمية.
So what's going on?
إذن ما الذي يجري؟
Well, I think there are two things.
حسنا، أعتقد أن هناك شيئين.
The first is that in a way, we're the victims of our own success.
الأوّل أنه بطريقة ما نحن ضحايا نجاحاتنا.
We've used up the easy wins from economic growth,
لقد تعودنا على الفوز السهل نتيجة النمو الاقتصادي،
and now we're moving on to harder problems.
والآن نحن ننتقل إلى مشاكل أصعب.
And also, we know that economic growth comes with costs as well as benefits.
كما نعلم أن النمو الاقتصادي يصاحبه تكاليف وفوائد.
There are costs to the environment, costs from new health problems like obesity.
هناك تكاليف تتعلق بالبيئة، والمشاكل الصحية الجديدة مثل السمنة.
So that's the bad news.
إذن هذا هو الخبر السيء.
We're not going to get to the Global Goals just by getting richer.
فنحن لن نُحقّق أهدافنا العالمية فقط عندما نُصبح أغنى.
So are the pessimists right?
فهل المتشائمؤن على حق؟
Well, maybe not.
حسنا، ربما لا.
Because the Social Progress Index also has some very good news.
لأن مؤشر النمو الاجتماعي يدلّ على أخبار جيدة.
Let me take you back to that regression line.
دعوني أرجع بكم لخط الانحدار.
So this is the average relationship between GDP and social progress,
هذه هي العلاقة التقريبية بين الناتج المحلي الإجمالي
and this is what our last forecast was based on.
والنمو الاجتماعي وهذا ما ارتكًزت عليه.
But as you saw already,
توقعاتنا الأخيرة ولكن كما ترون،
there is actually lots of noise around this trend line.
في الحقيقة أن هناك الكثير من الضجيج حول مسار الاتجاه.
What that tells us, quite simply,
وهذا يدلّ بكلّ بساطة،
is that GDP is not destiny.
على أن الناتج الداخلي الخام ليس مقدّرا.
We have countries that are underperforming
لدينا بلدان أدائها هزيل
on social progress, relative to their wealth.
فيما يتعلق بالنمو الاقتصادي، مقارنة بثروتهم.
Russia has lots of natural resource wealth,
تملك روسيا العديد من الثروات الطبيعية ،
but lots of social problems.
ولكن الكثير من المشاكل الاجتماعية.
China has boomed economically,
ازدهرت الصين اقتصاديا،
but hasn't made much headway on human rights or environmental issues.
ولكن لم تُحرز تقدّما على مستوى حقوق الإنسان والقضايا البيئيّة.
India has a space program and millions of people without toilets.
تملك الهند فضاء للبرمجة والملايين من الأشخاص بدون مراحيض.
Now, on the other hand, we have countries that are overperforming
حاليا، من ناحية أُخرى، لدينا بلدان ذات أداء عال
on social progress relative to their GDP.
على مستوى النمو الاجتماعي بالنسبة للناتج المحلي الإجمالي.
Costa Rica has prioritized education, health and environmental sustainability,
أعطت كوستاريكا الأولويّة للتعليم والصحة والبيئة بطريقة مستدامة،
and as a result, it's achieving a very high level of social progress,
وكنتيجة لذلك شهدت مستوى عال للنمو الاجتماعي،
despite only having a rather modest GDP.
بالرغم من الناتج المحلّي الإجمالي المنخفض.
And Costa Rica's not alone.
وليست كوستريكا فقط.
From poor countries like Rwanda to richer countries like New Zealand,
بدءًا بالبلدان الفقيرة مثل روندا وصولا إلى الأغنى مثل نيوزلندا،
we see that it's possible to get lots of social progress,
نلاحظ أنه بالإمكان تحقيق الكثير من النمو الاجتماعي،
even if your GDP is not so great.
حتى وإن لم يكن الناتج المحلي الإجمالي مرتفعا.
And that's really important, because it tells us two things.
وهذا مهم جدا لأنه يدلّ على شيئين.
First of all, it tells us that we already in the world have the solutions
أوّلا، يدلّ على وجود حلول في العالم
to many of the problems that the Global Goals are trying to solve.
للعديد من المشاكل التي تسعى الأهداف العالمية لحلّها.
It also tells us that we're not slaves to GDP.
وكما يدلّ على أننا لسنا عبيدا للناتج المحلي الإجمالي.
Our choices matter: if we prioritize the well-being of people,
اختياراتنا مهمة: إذا أعطينا الأولوية لرفاهية الناس،
then we can make a lot more progress than our GDP might expect.
فيمكننا تحقيق نمو أفضل من المتوقع استنادًا على الناتج المحلّي الإجمالي.
How much? Enough to get us to the Global Goals?
كم يكفي لتحقيق الأهداف العالمية؟
Well, let's look at some numbers.
لنلق نظرة على بعض الأرقام.
What we know already: the world today is scoring 61 on social progress,
ما نعرفه اليوم هو : أن العالم اليوم حقق نموا اجتماعيا بمعدّل 61،
and the place we want to get to is 75.
ونحن نريد بُلوغ 75.
If we rely on economic growth alone,
إذا اعتمدنا على النمو الاقتصادي فقط،
we're going to get to 62.4.
فسنصل إلى معدّل 62.4
So let's assume now that we can get the countries that are currently
إذن فلنفترض أنه يمكننا إيصال تلك البلدان ذات الأداء المنخفض
underperforming on social progress -- the Russia, China, Indias --
على مستوى النمو الاجتماعي مثل -- روسيا والصين والهند --
just up to the average.
لبلوغ المعدّل.
How much social progress does that get us?
ماهو مدى النمو الاجتماعي الذي يجب بلوغه؟
Well, that takes us to 65.
حسنا، هذا يُحيلنا إلى 65.
It's a bit better, but still quite a long way to go.
هذا أفضل بقليل، ولكن ما يزال الطريق طويلا.
So let's get a little bit more optimistic and say,
إذن فلنكن متفائلين قليلا،
what if every country gets a little bit better
ماذا لو شهد كل بلد تحسّنا ضئيلا
at turning its wealth into well-being?
في تحويل ثروته إلى رفاهية الأشخاص؟
Well then, we get to 67.
إلى حين ذلك، سنصل إلى 67.
And now let's be even bolder still.
والآن فلنكن أكثر شجاعة.
What if every country in the world chose to be like Costa Rica
ماذا لو اختار كل بلد في العالم أن يكون مثل كوستاريكا
in prioritizing human well-being,
في إعطاء الأولوية إلى رفاهية الأشخاص،
using its wealth for the well-being of its citizens?
باستعمال ثروتهم بهدف توفير الرفاهية؟
Well then, we get to nearly 73, very close to the Global Goals.
حسنا ، حينها سنصل إلى 73، قريبون جدا من الأهداف العالمية.
Can we achieve the Global Goals?
هل بإمكاننا تحقيق الأهداف العالمية؟
Certainly not with business as usual.
بالتأكيد ليس بلغة التجارة كالمعتاد.
Even a flood tide of economic growth is not going to get us there,
حتى طوفان جارف من النمو الاقتصادي لن يحقّق لنا ذلك،
if it just raises the mega-yachts and the super-wealthy
إن كان يزيد عدد اليخوت وفائقي الثراء
and leaves the rest behind.
ويترك الباقي خلفه.
If we're going to achieve the Global Goals we have to do things differently.
إذا أردنا تحقيق الأهداف العالمية فإن علينا القيام بالأشياء بطريقة مختلفة.
We have to prioritize social progress, and really scale solutions
علينا إعطاء الأولوية للنمو الاجتماعي،
around the world.
ووضع حلول حقيقية حول العالم.
I believe the Global Goals are a historic opportunity,
أُؤمن أن الأهداف العالمية هي فرصة تاريخية،
because the world's leaders have promised to deliver them.
لأن زعماء العالم وعدوا بتسليمها.
Let's not dismiss the goals or slide into pessimism;
دعونا لا نحيد عن الأهداف أو نغرق في التشاؤم،
let's hold them to that promise.
فلنف بذلك الوعد.
And we need to hold them to that promise by holding them accountable,
ونحن في حاجة لأن نفي بالوعد، بالمحاسبة،
tracking their progress all the way through the next 15 years.
متابعة التقدم خلال 15 سنة القادمة.
And I want to finish by showing you
وأريد أن أختم بعرض
a way to do that, called the People's Report Card.
طريقة القيام بذلك والتي تُسمّى "بطاقة التقرير الشعبية".
The People's Report Card brings together all this data into a simple framework
هذه البطاقات تجمع كل هذه البيانات في إطار بسيط
that we'll all be familiar with from our school days,
والتي سنتعود عليها من أيام المدرسة،
to hold them to account.
ونضعها في الحسبان.
It grades our performance on the Global Goals
تقيّم أداءنا حول الأهداف العالمية
on a scale from F to A,
من "F" إلى"A"
where F is humanity at its worst, and A is humanity at its best.
حيث ترمز F إلى الإنسانية في أسوء حالتها وA إلى الإنسانية في أفضل حالاتها.
Our world today is scoring a C-.
العالم اليوم يُعطي درجة C منخفض.
The Global Goals are all about getting to an A,
والأهداف العالمية في طريقها إلى الحصول على درجة A،
and that's why we're going to be updating the People's Report Card annually,
ولذلك سنقوم بتحديث بطاقات التقرير الشعبية سنويا،
for the world and for all the countries of the world,
للعالم ولكل بلدان العالم،
so we can hold our leaders to account
لكي نتمكن من توجيه قادتنا
to achieve this target and fulfill this promise.
لتحقيق هذا الهدف والوعد.
Because getting to the Global Goals will only happen if we do things differently,
لأن تحقيق الأهداف العالمية لا يكون إلا بالقيام بالأشياء بطريقة مختلفة،
if our leaders do things differently,
إذا قام قادتنا بالأشياء بطريقة مختلفة،
and for that to happen, that needs us to demand it.
ولكي يتحقق ذلك، يجب أن نطلبه.
So let's reject business as usual.
إذن لنتخل عن المعاملات التجارية كالعادة.
Let's demand a different path.
دعونا نطلب مسارا مختلفا.
Let's choose the world that we want.
فلنختر العالم الذي نريده.
Thank you.
شكرا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Bruno Giussani: Thank you, Michael.
برونو غيوساني: شكرا لك مايكل.
Michael, just one question: the Millennium Development Goals
مايكل لدي سؤال واحد فقط : الأهداف الإنمائية للألفية
established 15 years ago,
التي وُضعت منذ 15 سنة،
they were kind of applying to every country
كان يتم تطبيقها على كل بلد حسب التقريب
but it turned out to be really a scorecard for emerging countries.
ولكن اتضح أنها كانت بطاقة النتائج للبلدان الناشئة.
Now the new Global Goals are explicitly universal.
حاليّا الأهداف العالمية أصبحت بشكل واضح عالمية.
They ask for every country to show action and to show progress.
يطلبون من كل بلد إظهار عملهم ومدى تطورهم.
How can I, as a private citizen, use the report card
كيف يمكنني كمواطن، أن أستعمل بطاقة التقرير
to create pressure for action?
لخلق نوع من الضغط للحث على العمل؟
Michael Green: This is a really important point; it's a big shift in priorities --
مايكل غرين: هذه حقا نقطة مهمة جدا، إنه تحوّل في الأولويات --
it's no longer about poor countries and just poverty.
إنه ليس فقط حول البلدان الفقيرة والفقر فقط.
It's about every country.
بل حول كل بلد.
And every country is going to have challenges in getting to the Global Goals.
وسيواجه كل بلد مجموعة من التحديات لتحقيق الأهداف العالمية.
Even, I'm sorry to say, Bruno, Switzerland has got to work to do.
حتى، أنا آسف لقول ذلك، برونو، سويسرا لديها عمل للقيام به.
And so that's why we're going to produce these report cards in 2016
ولذلك سنقوم بإنتاج بطاقات التقرير في سنة 2016.
for every country in the world.
لكل بلد في العالم.
Then we can really see, how are we doing?
ثم يمكننا حقا رؤية كيف سنقوم بذلك؟
And it's not going to be rich countries scoring straight A's.
ولن تكون هناك بلدان غنية ولديها درجة A.
And that, then, I think, is to provide a point of focus
ثم أعتقد كذلك أن ذلك يتم بتوفير نقطة للتركيز
for people to start demanding action and start demanding progress.
للأشخاص ليبدؤوا بطلب العمل والتطور.
BG: Thank you very much.
برونو غيوساني: شكرا لك كثيرا.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)